[Music]
ever thought about a master's degree to
advance your career as a software
developer the UC Irvine 16-month
professionally oriented master of
software engineering program is made for
you taught by experts in the field the
program combines hands-on experiences
and fundamentals and latest trends with
professional development for successful
careers after graduation
hurry applications for fall 2019 are due
December 15th visit MSE ICS UCI GDU to
learn more and start your application
today this is software engineering radio
the podcast for professional developers
on the web at se - radio net se radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size we're
moving infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/sz radio hello this is Kishore Bhatia
for software engineering video today's
episode is about the tedium ecosystem
and decentralized computing
infrastructure and applications with
John Crane John is the founder of pic
serie
and super air the platform for rare
digital native collectable assets on it
helium John was previously at consensus
working on it helium based products
followed by his role as the head of
product at block apps where he helped
build and launch an idiom smart contract
developer platform
welcome to software engineering radio
John thanks for having me ashore today
we are going to talk about it helium and
and the ETD umeko system that we have
seen evolve in the last couple years for
a decentralized computing platform will
also overview different comparable
technologies that exist today
and that are evolving in the space the
tedium also has the concept of smart
contracts so we will run through some
examples of how smart contracts have
evolved in the theorem ecosystem there
is also the concept of applications that
are developed on its helium platform
known as decentralized apps so also
going through those examples would be
helpful with John here who has
experience developing them and deploying
them and then we lastly cover the
developer ecosystem to actually get to
the apps and writing smart contracts on
aetherium so John will dive into the
history of etherium and also go through
where we are today and why is this
relevant in computing starting with what
is it helium sure so at its core cerium
is an open-source software platform
that's based on blockchain technology
and so what's special about aetherium is
it enables developers to build and
deploy decentralized applications and so
what that means is the theorem is a
little bit different from other sort of
blockchain platforms in that you can
actually embed parts of the application
into the blockchain itself and this is
pretty interesting because you know
store the data that gets yeah you know
updated by those pieces of code living
in the blockchain nobody's actually
control of them so once you you know
sort of like right up your script and
deploy it to the chain that code is uh
it's sitting out there for anybody to
use and it's you're not gonna be able to
update it which is a you know it's sort
of a different paradigm then we're used
to you know we're really used to this
sort of CI environment where it's like
oh there's a bug let's just push a you
know push a commit to master we'll just
go ahead and update the whole app so
it's an interesting paradigm to to
program in that's interesting uh you
mentioned something about embedding code
within the blockchain I do want to
double click on that and you know go
deep when we come into the components of
the ecosystem but you know just to
just to get into the details of why why
now and why is it that we need it in in
the current ecosystem so why is it
helium needed yeah great great question
probably lots of the listeners are you
know somewhat up to date on you know
some of the recent sort of Cambridge
analytical scandal with Facebook data
ownership and privacy and uh things like
that and so basically what aetherium
allows by sort of you know having this
totally decentralized you know aspect to
it is a you know users and builders of
these apps they can sort of place things
and control the user for example you
know just pieces of data that the user
has control on the chain you know
they're the etherium sort of gives
developers the tools you need to build
applications and then these applications
give users the tools to sort of you know
have a much greater control over the
gist their identity and data in relation
to the application so you know there's
no one central authority sort of all the
data is out there the data can be
encrypted or not this is sort of like
you know up to the developers themselves
but we now have sort of a totally open
and secure database for developers to
leverage and you know in the at the end
of the day this is a huge benefit to
consumers because these big you know
data silos and data aggregators you know
they're pretty vulnerable to you know
misuse of Terms of Service as we saw
with Cambridge analytic a misuse and
sort of vulnerabilities for as far as
like you know people hacking into
systems last year we had that huge data
breach with Equifax and it seems to me
like we're learning that uh you know we
sort of just need better standards and
aetherium is you know a tool that kind
of facilitates an easy way to implement
some of these improvements and there are
commoditized you know cloud platforms
today to develop a lot of applications
that are distributed in nature how is it
helium
different in that sense and you
mentioned the word decentralized so I
wanted to just capture for the audience
the difference - sure
so the Tyrians are decentralized you
know a smart contract platform so each
you know node in the network it's a you
know mining contributing to the security
of the network has a copy of all of the
smart contract data so they're sort of
ensuring that um you know no one is
cheating or manipulating that data
you know you as a user and controller
your keys so if you have an aetherium
account and you know you want to
interact with the smart contract or
decentralized application only you're
gonna be able to do that you know the
only the person with the private key can
go update something in the application
that that key has access to so you now
have this greatly improved level of
security that's sort of just inherent in
the platform
you know Postgres is a really good
database but you know there's not sort
of this level of public and private key
encryption so like baked into the core
of it you know you can add really good
user level permissions and all sorts of
security features on top but really
aetherium has all those things or just
like inherently built into the system I
see I do want to get into the details of
the components later in the show and
that's something that you mentioned
something around the the decentralized
nature the inbuilt security on you know
how data is stored within each node and
the fact that they are actually
replicated across each node and and
everything is you know is always
persisted so you can actually do a quick
audit as well what does the ecosystem
look like today with aetherium is it the
first one you know where where are we in
terms of where all the blocks in
ecosystem components are sure
so yeah aetherium definitely was not the
first blockchain but as far as smart
contract platforms it definitely was the
first and has the most adoption
so just ecosystem in general you know
bitcoins sort of the OG it's been around
for a long time you know there's the
interesting debate between Bitcoin and
Bitcoin cash happening but you know
bitcoins still quite relevant
wouldn't you know it's probably not
gonna go away anytime soon we have you
know the Lightning Network is sort of up
and running in beta which is super
interesting this is you know an
interesting step forward for payments as
far as smart contract platforms that's
it atheria miss definitely has the most
developer adoption and I'd say the most
applications actually in production
right now that said it's not the only
platform out there so there's also a
platform called block stack you know
they're taking a disc slightly different
approach they have a concept of like
virtualized chains and I think they're
trying to be sort of blockchain agnostic
but you know they have this concept of
decentralized applications you know
they're really working on data ownership
and privacy also I think you know it's
not quite as decentralized nature as
aetherium
and you know there's pros and cons to
this so it's sort of like you know how
interested are you in the decentralized
security in the nature of the
application and I think a number the
other ones are similar so EOS is not
actually they don't have a working
production blockchain but they are
working on building smart contract
solutions they have sort of this
federated node delegated proof of stake
you know lots of interesting sort of
buzzwords around how consensus is
achieved but essentially you know some
of the sort of like higher throughput
block chains have the pro is that it you
know they have they achieved consensus
really fast the con be that consensus is
achieved in a more centralized manner so
you know some people might be critical
of how they're doing that right and in
terms of the trends that that have
happened over you know the last 20-30
years in in computing and also like
recently within the the post Internet
era what what is driving this this
innovation and also we want to get into
the the aspects of what is driving
adoption so let's begin with what is
driving the the innovation like
aetherium in the community sure you know
we had I heard a concept recently that
I'd never heard this term before but
sort of the it was like the distributed
web Ice Age new we've had a lot of these
peer-to-peer technologies
you know at our fingertips for a while
and they maybe just weren't sort of
brought together and you know
productized and you know in a way that
was friendly for a developer or consumer
to use so a lot of these concepts have
been around you know we have distributed
file sharing you know all sorts of
different distributed applications but
there's sort of been this resurgence in
you know research in the area and you
know just sort of general interest I'm
sure a huge part of it is due to the
speculative nature you know a lot of
these you know companies and groups
issuing tokens but I think ultimately
it's deads you know it's offer for the
best because there are some pretty you
know there's some pretty critical
problems with how we sort of manage
identity on the Internet
managing data ownership you know we
still have some some pretty big problems
that require you know pretty interesting
solutions and I think a lot of the
innovation and drive is coming from your
people acknowledging that these are sort
of pretty serious problems that need to
be tackled about you and and we'll get
into the details of community you know
in a bit but in terms of adoption what
what have you seen in the recent years
we've definitely seen a lot of hype on
you know the beginning of the blockchain
hype cycle you know 2015 2016 you
mentioned you know rightly about the
speculative nature of most of these with
tokens coming into picture but there's
definitely a lot of you know technology
work that has gone in to you know to
push these things towards general public
use what what is the kind of adoption
that you have seen recently this is far
as adoption do you mean like from a
development standpoint or for like more
like consumer facing applications like
with a good question I think let's begin
with consumer facing applications and
then we'll do a deep dive as we get into
ecosystem sure so yeah I'd say there's
been a lot of interesting developments
in the consumer application area you
know one of the interesting things is I
think we're still in a little bit of an
int
structure building phase so as far as
the really good consumer applications I
there's a so this idea of like you know
adapt browser or decentralized app
browsers and there's sort of an
interesting combination of like just a
regular web browser but also kind of a
chat application and then also a key
management solution so you know a lot of
these decentralized applications and you
know one of the interesting features is
that you're the only person who can sign
a message from your account and so you
sort of need to have this key management
layer and message signing feature kind
of built into the browser natively
there's a pretty good chrome plug-in for
doing this it's called meta mask it's
probably you know one of the most used
I'd say it's not really a consumer
application but it's kind of like a
consumer tool and then there's some
pretty good mobile key signing that
browsers
one of them's called toe sheets put out
by coinbase another really great one is
a trust wallet that's a open source ios
and android app and that's a pretty
thing a pretty small team out in san
francisco so they these tools you know
kind of coming into their maturity have
sort of allowed some of these other
other apps to be built on top I'd say
the most successful and kind of most
used apps that are out right now or kind
of these like trading applications or
marketplaces so there's a number of
different token trading applications
that are out there crypto kitties is
many of the listeners have probably
heard about you know almost like clogged
the theory of network for a while yeah
I'd say most of the consumer apps are
kind of like trading focused or you know
have some aspect of this token trading
so built into the application right now
right I think you're also mentioned the
the use of identity and and data privacy
on you know things like the the tap
browser and also the messaging and chat
apps so that that's pretty interesting
as to how they are evolving getting into
the the main components
that's basically you know our view of it
helium the ecosystem we talked about the
innovation and option happening I think
we wanted to also look at the
architecture of what we understand it's
helium today so I you know if if I'm
looking back at you know 2014 I was
actually you know like looking at this
one world computer aspect of with helium
the vision at least was that it's
basically a a giant computer that is you
know decentralized and distributed
across the world with many connected
components and that reminded me of this
this code from one of the Sun cofounders
also by the name of John John gage and
he said network the network is the
computer and I feel like that's that's
probably what is coming true with
something like it helium that has all
these connected nodes with you know a
replica of each and every aspect of the
ledger that has the different
transactions blocks events and even you
mentioned code that I want to get into
so John let's dive deeper into the
components of etherium the etherium
stack sure so all the different
components in the etherium stack are
outlined in aetherium yellow paper so
this is sort of just the mathematical
and technical spec that outlines
everything but at the core a theory 'm
is different from blockchains like
bitcoin and that bitcoin has a sort of
you TXO model or unspent transaction
output model that's how they keep track
of you know who has which balance
theorem took a different approach and on
aetherium at the core we have this idea
of an account so there's two different
types of accounts first there are
external accounts and these are accounts
that the private keys are controlled by
you know humans and there's also
internal accounts and so these are
accounts that get created when people
sort of upload and create a smart
contract so these live within the system
and these can you know have code
attached to them which is different to
the external accounts where you know
humans control
because there's a no code property so
those are probably the two main
differences for those different types of
accounts and so then one level up from
that we probably have sort of the the
state so this is basically an
instantaneous snapshot of like what are
you know any like data feel they're like
anything that's been changed in the
theorem state is sort of sort of the
just current state of everything so
there's two different types we have as
memory and storage so memory state would
be things that get updated during
execution of a smart contract but don't
get persisted so you know this could be
you know potentially they could counter
in a for loop or something like that
something that we're gonna you know
update state momentarily but then we
don't need to keep around and storage is
you know if we're adding a new person to
our you know multi-sig wallet or
something we're gonna have we're gonna
want to keep this data around basically
forever so those are the two different
types of state and the way people update
state is by you know either just sending
an ether transaction so a simple
transfer or calling a smart contract
method and with general-purpose
programming languages we needed some
features to kind of prevent people from
you know running an infinite loop and
crashing the entire system you can
imagine if you're running an influent
infinite loop on thousands of computers
around the world this is gonna be pretty
expensive and wasteful and so aetherium
came up with this concept of gas so gas
is basically sort of the price you pay
for each computation you'd like to
perform on the network so say you wanna
you know update a value you know it used
to be one and now things have moved
along and it's time to change it to two
and we're gonna update this value in
storage so every node and the network is
going to have this updated this is a
pretty expensive operation I think one
of the most expensive
things you can do in aetherium is to
update storage and so you're gonna pay
the most gas to do perform an operation
like that where as something sort of a
memory performing operation has a much
lower gas cost than a storage state
update operation so every time you make
a transaction in the theory um if you're
calling a smart contract the system will
estimate what's the gas costs gonna be
how much ether do you need to provide
with the transaction just to make sure
it finishes executing and also then the
so ultimately the gas is sort of solving
the halting problem where you would just
cause the network to stop working sort
of I like using up all the resources and
so you know well I was talking about
that I was talking you know I was just
talking about executing smart contracts
and the way this happens in etherium is
through transactions pretty much
everything is a transaction whether
you're just you know sending somebody
five bucks or you know you're deploying
a new financial derivative so it all
works through just transactions and
message passing and basically the
transaction will be built
you know client side possibly in your
browser maybe on a mobile phone you know
or a desktop app this will be compiled
based on all the data you want to have
in that message and you'll actually sign
the message with your private key before
submitting it to the network so this
ensures somebody can't go in and tamper
with the data that you'd like to send
and it also is pretty convenient because
you could actually sign a message and
then just give it to somebody else to
submit to the network so I can
potentially sign a message locally in my
computer email it to you cash or and
then you can submit it to the network
for me and this is pretty cool there's
some interesting use cases here where
you might want to you know potentially
send money from cold wallet you know
sort of offline storage to a hot wallet
and you could just sign that transaction
on your offline computer and then you
could put it on the USB stick and
get over to a different computer and
submit that to the network so this is
you know interesting features of the
message signing and I guess the next
level up in the stack we have you know
these blocks so the transactions get
ordered in blocks basically what the you
know the nodes are doing is they're sort
of mining these new blocks is ordering
transactions and then trying to tell all
the other nodes of the network which is
the the best block that they should they
should have so the most recent block
that exists so the nodes are sort of
accepting all these transactions
ordering them trying to you know mind
the mind the block using the proof of
work consensus algorithm and then as
soon as they mind this block then
they're gonna go ahead and tell
everybody else gossip style about this
block that they've just discovered and
so yep as you I just mentioned proof of
work so proof of work as a consensus
algorithm is basically the nodes trying
to compute a specific hash so you know
statistically yeah it's gonna be hard to
kind of guess what this hash needs to be
so they key so it's designed you know
based on how many nodes are on the
network they try to make it a little
harder and I think it scales up linearly
with each node they try to keep a
consistent block time based on the
difficulty you know the more nodes on
the network basically the harder it is
gonna be to actually mine one of these
blocks does that make sense yeah I think
yeah so every time you're saying as the
chain you know becomes more and more
heavier with more and more transactions
and blocks coming in it becomes more
difficult to mine a new clock yeah
that's correct
yeah in terms of this account you
mentioned the account has a specific
every account has a specific account
address and and like what else is within
an account let's see yes so there are
there's a number of different properties
on the account you have some of the
cryptographic sort of features
you know slightly above my my pay grade
for knowing exactly how the sort of like
the elliptic curve signatures work but
there's a number of different properties
there to kind of ensure you know that
nobody else is going to be sending you
know sending transactions from this
account so you can have you know
accounts have a balance so this is sort
of like the amount of ether associated
with this account so that gets used for
the different gas and you know just
simple transaction sending that I
mentioned before right and then also
some of these you know different
signature properties gotcha so what is
the word state you know like what is
that maintained gotcha so each node on
the network is actually going to
maintain this state locally so and if
you're you know spinning up a new node
say you're on AWS and you want to you
know try mining some ether you can you
know download the software compile it
and start running and you're gonna
actually download the entire state from
all the nodes you're connected to and
you're gonna be maintaining your own
property so anytime a new transaction
comes in that you think is gonna be
committed to go to a block
you're gonna update state locally and
then you know tell everybody else say I
have this new transaction you should
also run it and update your local state
gotcha yep so I think you you mentioned
something around transactions can you
elaborate a bit more about you know
transactions different types you know is
it always all about you know accounts
passing ether from one account to
another or are there different types of
you know things going on sure so there
are different types so all the
transactions are just you know messages
to the network so we're just you know
telling the network hey I want to do
something but there's sort of two
different types of things you can do so
you could do a you know simple send
transaction so this would be passing
ether from one account to another so you
know if I have an offline
count I wanted to send it to my online
account connected to the Internet that's
one type of transaction or you know if
I'm paying you back for the PT II bought
last night sure I could just you know do
a simple send transaction and that the
other type of transaction is when you're
actually interacting with a smart
contract so if you want to you know sort
of do you'll call any smart contract out
on the network you send that message
sort of signifying that like here's this
address I want to talk to and you
there's a you know in the transaction
there's a data field so when you're
calling a smart contract you sort of say
in the data field I want to talk to this
account and I'm actually going to send
this piece of data also that you know
says exactly which smart contract method
you'd like to call and then how do you
keep track of like the transactions
having them completed or you know
something failed is there some kind of
logging mechanism yeah so etherium has a
sort of an event log system that kind of
helps maintain sort of you know a little
bit of metadata about what's actually
happening in the system so yeah we
there's a you can you know kind of pull
these event logs so as soon as you
submit a transaction you instantly get
sort of a transaction receipt then you
can kind of watch and see to make sure
you know either
or at least to know so you know as you
know this is an enormous distributed
system you're not always sure your
transactions gonna you know make it into
a block you don't know you know how
which block it's going to get into see
you get a receipt and then you can kind
of pull the logs to check and see okay
is there sort of a verification then
that my transaction was actually
included so so then the concept of smart
contracts you know they come in and
basically play within these different
areas that we mentioned around blocks
transactions message sending right yeah
so if I am creating a new contract as a
developer for the first time and let's
start with simple storage
you go over maybe the flow of what
happens in the network when when a
contract gets created sure today so the
first thing would happen a beer
developer you would actually to compile
your smart contract and you'd get two
things you'd have the the ABI the
application binary interface that kind
of says okay here's what's in my smart
contract here's all the different
methods you know variable names and sort
of data like that and then you'd also
get a chunk of byte code and so this is
what you're actually going to upload to
the network and is what's going to
basically update the update the storage
and live there in aetherium so that beam
compiled the smart contract you're gonna
go ahead and sign the transaction saying
hey you know this account would like to
deploy this new smart contract to the
network here's all here's the byte code
of the smart contract so here's sort of
all the you know the business logic and
then you would submit that just like any
other transaction all the nodes once
they pick it up are then going to store
that byte code in their state and attach
it to a new account so when you deploy a
new smart contract to the network you
get a transaction receipt like hey we
got your we got your transaction we know
you're trying to do something and then
upon success like successful creation
which means that all the other nodes in
network have you know committed this
transaction to a block you're gonna get
the address of that smart contract back
and so this is what you need to then you
know interact with the smart contract
once it's uploaded and like going down
to the machine level out the part of the
protocol that basically processes all of
this you know transaction work and then
also helps creating new blocks or
validating them is is a machine right
can you go down into like what is that
machine like
sure so the the low level you know
etherium is basically a few things but
but you're sort of you know so I get the
core we have this you know if he doesn't
do that much besides agree upon you know
which transactions are valid so we have
all these nodes on the network they're
talking to each other communicating
about new transactions that are coming
in and they're performing what we call
you know proof of work and basically
what this means is that each transaction
that comes into a node they're gonna do
a quick check to make sure you know does
this account have enough ether there to
actually run this transaction was it the
was has this message been signed as the
transaction been signed by the proper
account you know some simple validation
and then they're gonna include it in the
block they're trying to mine as soon as
they you know mind this block you know
correctly calculate the hash within a
specific range they're gonna then tell
all the other machines on the network
okay I just found the new best block you
guys should all sort of update and start
mining a new block because I just found
the best one is that whether you were
now you're getting a key George gotcha
no yeah I think that that's that's a
good sequence of what is happening and
then there's this whole virtual machine
concept right what is that sure so the
you know the virtual machine is kind of
it's similar to you know any other
virtual machine that you might be
running a java virtual machine at home
on your computer right now but basically
this is certain you know this is sort of
the meta layer on top of agreement about
transactions and the virtual machine is
what processes all the smart contract
codes so when somebody wants to interact
with the smart contract call a method
and you know do something to the state
the virtual machine is where the actual
ex
fusion happens so you know if you're
calling a method that you know it's
gonna update a bunch of different
properties that you have stored you know
in a struct or an array this execution
actually takes place in the virtual
machine on each computer on network
gotcha and in the way the network gets
consensus you know what is what is
happening between these machines are
they just broadcasting these messages
that I found a new block or you know
this is my canonical chain that I'm on
what is what is happening in between
these nodes sure
so it basically all the nodes they're
competing they're trying to you know
they're trying to find the new best
block they call it the fastest cuz
they'd like the remaining reward so each
node is basically taking it's sort of
ingesting accounts that are trans excuse
me transactions that are being submitted
to it it's ordering it's validating
these transactions and then sort of
packaging them up into a block in the
hopes that they'll be the first one to
compute the new hash that needs to be
computed then once they whoever finds
this block first kind of tells the
network and say you had two different
nodes on different sides of the world
basically find the new new best block
approximately at the same time they
would tell all the nodes they were
connected to and whoever's best block
propagated to over 50% of the network
first would be the next one that got
included so you might have you know if
you were sort of waiting you're you know
you're pulling this transaction receipt
to see if you got included in a block
you might get a false positive like oh
it looks like you're included in block
you know five million or five million in
one and then you might see oh just
kidding it's still pending so you know
there's this reordering that can happen
based on the number of nodes that you
know kind of find the new best block and
whoever gets a
jeordy will win so ultimately you might
have a no do you tell your friend like
hey I found this new best block you
should add it and if they already have a
block number so that they already have
block five million in one they're gonna
tell you like no you're totally wrong
there's this this is the block you
should have this is block five million
in one so it's kind of all these
different nodes are negotiating with
each other and you do have this is sort
of why you know I think in Bitcoin you
wait six confirmations to be sure that
there won't be a reorder and I think in
aetherium since the block times are so
much lower
I think you weighed approximately like
twenty to a hundred block confirmations
before you're sure there won't be a
chain reorder gotcha so yeah I think
this is a good time to deep dive into
the security aspect of this like how
does all this make the network you know
more secure and I know that there's many
different aspects of it so like pick
particular you know aspects that you
have seen or have read about or
experienced sure so yeah this the
proof-of-work mechanism kind of makes
the network secure and that based on
like the distributed hashing power there
isn't one party he's gonna be able to
sort of rewrite the chain based on what
they want so you know ultimately block
chains and proof of work or solving this
the first thing they solve is the double
spend problem so if I build up a
transaction saying I'm sending you to
shore one ether and if I write another
transaction saying I'm also you know
sending Alice one ether I could submit
them to two different nodes they would
start propagating out but whichever
transaction sort of reached majority
consensus like a bunch of the nodes the
network agreed it would then throw out
sort of the false one so I can never
really achieve you know this this lie
that I've tried to pay both of you the
same either so let's sort of I think the
main security feature that having all
these nodes is that
they sort of keep individuals honest and
then also you know sort of prevent other
people from kind of rewriting history
which I guess is sort of the same thing
they're kind of just keeping you honest
and making sure you're sort of playing
within their constraints right gotcha
and then the individual nodes you're
saying that because this is all about
consensus across the network it is not
too much of a concern that an individual
node could be compromised right yes so
the the idea here is that if an
individual node is compromised the
general hashing power of the rest of the
network is that it won't matter and so
that's sort of how the system was
designed it's really the original design
the Satoshi outlines in his white paper
is that there will be bad actors in the
system and that's sort of why you have
this consensus set up like this
so this is - acknowledging that bad
actors will exist and it would sort of
won't matter as long as you have bunch
of different nodes participating in the
network who you know - aren't controlled
by one party gotcha
digital ocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy manage and scale
applications of any size we're moving
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software that customers love
with thousands of in-depth tutorials in
an active community we provide the
support you need digitalocean stands out
of the crowd due to its simplicity and
high performance with no billing
surprises try digitalocean for free by
getting a one hundred dollar
infrastructure credit at doco / SC radio
and you know beyond consensus I wanted
to you know understand this whole
concept of you know governance so within
a tedium you know or even before within
Bitcoin you know we've seen miners you
know trying to basically you know define
the path forward or sometimes you know
we've seen for King so there's different
ways to update the network to update the
nodes but there's also different ways to
like achieve consensus amongst the human
beings behind these mining nodes so can
you can you go down into like what what
does this mean and then how does one
update the you know the protocol itself
yeah there's that you know that's good
there's a couple things it's one of the
funny things you know we talk a lot
about you know immutable you know the
blockchain is immutable there's no way
we can change it but ultimately there's
a bunch of humans on the other side of
all the nodes maintaining the software
you know maintaining the state that
they're you know that the nodes are
pointing to so we do need to you know
rely on humans and they're they're also
a big part of the the equation here so
there's a you know as far as forking is
concerned when you want to you know
update the protocol you might be doing
something like changing the data
structure in the block or maybe adding a
new property to a transaction or
something like this and there's two ways
to do it so you can sort of a soft fork
would be what we've just added a new
property to a transaction maybe and so
old nodes you know say they're running
you know version 5 and we're updating to
version 6 and now we're gonna allow this
new data field that performs some
feature an old node might still be able
to process the new transaction because
it has everything it's looking for it's
still able to validate that it's good
but it doesn't perform any extra new
feature that we've added whereas if you
had version 6 you'd see this new field
and then you might do some extra work or
do something else you know so this is
this idea of the soft fork where old
nodes can still participate but they
don't know they don't necessarily
benefit or do anything that you know
they don't they're not acknowledging
that the change happened whereas a hard
fork basically the old if you had an old
version of the software your nodes no
longer gonna be able to communicate with
the network and so you have to update
and you know this can be contentious you
sort of have to come to consensus as
humans and say ok everybody we're gonna
hard fork at midnight tomorrow make sure
you update your node otherwise you're
gonna stop you're basically going to
be able to process blocks anymore and
you know you'll no longer be
contributing to the network so there's
this interesting layer of sort of human
consensus that has to happen before we
can get the machines to come to
consensus which is definitely pretty
interesting sure
and and the Hart folks have also been in
place as one of the mechanisms to maybe
fix a security gap or you know something
that you know probably is causing say
you know a particular you know hack to
be then immediately fixed by doing a
protocol update or a heartful is that is
that also right yeah that's definitely
one of the reasons that hard works
happen one you know there's been a
couple examples of this in a theory I'm
one of the more popular or like what
yeah I think the most popular client is
the the go implementation and a couple
years ago but the etherium developer
conference in Shanghai the morning of
the conference which I think was you
know timed pretty coincidentally I think
this is definitely happened on purpose
but basically there was a memory leak
for a certain type of transaction where
you could you know sort of caused the
node to fail by submitting this like
specific type of transaction so
basically the network was under a DDoS
attack with these transactions that
caused memory leaks and everyone had to
coordinate you know there's a couple
different new there's a is the rest
implementation made by parody and
there's a few different implementations
that people use so basically people were
you know furiously trying to hotfix
to you know and then implement this fork
so they sort of like hot fix the bug
update all the software you know release
the new releases and then kind of
coordinated with everybody like okay
everybody switched this new version we
fixed the fix the memory leak and yeah
so those know interesting and exciting
to say the least that's a very good
example in even the you know the world
of software development then faster
releases you know like you
think about it at a more open source you
know open government open governance
model this could be done with foot with
forking you know with your the community
across the globe whereas we've seen
problems releasing software just within
a company which has all the resources at
its will and and we still don't go to
market quickly so yeah it's a it's an
interesting thing to see like how the
governance of you know the community
within an open-source model you know
completely EIP and you know GRC driven
has has moved towards you know this fast
update even though you know a lot of
times it feels slow just because you
know as you mentioned earlier the
scalability and the other bigger changes
to the protocol takes time yeah
absolutely it's a it's it's very
interesting to see you know when
everything's happened in this open
environment you know it's the the
attacks can be just as coordinated as
the you know constructive you know
software building and delivering so it's
definitely a sort of a new way to you
know think about the software
development process great so we covered
the components of you know if he looked
at ATM virtual machines what is the
overall definition of you know different
components that an EVM is is composed
off and then how do you actually
interact with that let's go on to the
you know the way people develop apps for
aetherium what are these mechanisms that
people use to develop apps sure I'd say
the you know a lot of the tooling
luckily can be you know pretty similar
to things were used to you know so sort
of like you know front-end architecture
for an application you can kind of pick
your flavor you know if it's a iOS app
or web app or you know anything like
that it's gonna be a pretty standard
architecture the one big difference yeah
at least for aetherium where you know
that's where most of my experiences I'm
certainly you know developing and
managing these smart contracts so I'd
say in the etherium ecosystem
probably the you know most used and
popular tool for smart contract
development and management is a tool
called truffle and so this tool well you
know kind of help you figure out how to
like set up your tests and you know how
to deploy to different networks in
aetherium there's a number test networks
that sort of simulate the live net you
know so there's actual nodes kind of
mining and producing ether on these
different networks and so you're gonna
have you know your smart contract
deployed to at least maybe like a local
network that has superfast block times
for you to do development then you might
deploy to you know rinkeby or one of
these other test networks that you know
has a slightly slower block times and
simulates the live net a little bit more
and then you'll also be deploying the
app to the live net and it is a little
bit interesting because to interact with
the smart contract once it's deployed
you kind of need to have so this
metadata file that kind of contains all
the different function it has some
mappings between like the function names
and you know what the smart contract
actually looks like so there are you
know some considerations for sort of new
architecture considerations that are you
know are a little bit different than in
general but you know luckily a lot of
the tooling is the same and it's sort of
just this you know keeping track of
these files they're called the API or
application binary interface so you do
have to keep these JSON files somewhere
within the front end of the app whether
it's you know iOS or a web app but
everything else is a you know somewhat
standard which is kind of nice I guess I
would like to say Apple is not the only
tool for doing this there's a project
called maker that's working on one of
these tokens that's it's called the
stable coin so it sort of is supposed to
be like a price stable less bottle token
and they built a lot of their own
tooling that I've heard really good
things about I think it's DAP tools or
something like that
and yeah there's a couple other sort of
smart contract management and you know
deployment tools concur that's pretty
interesting view of the development
ecosystem on in tedium so just to sum it
up you mentioned the the overall
architecture of an of an actual
decentralized app would be comprised of
the the it helium protocol layer itself
to blockchain which is decentralized and
then on top of that you've got the smart
contract ecosystem so you have an
application smart contract there is
sitting within that you know within that
blockchain layer but also that is the
one that the developer has the access to
in terms of modifying the application
putting in the the business logic there
and then you can use the more famous you
know frameworks for developing front-end
you know API is into that app but
there's a bit of like the ABI interface
that you mentioned which is the
application binary interface that has to
be known to the front-end to be able to
interact with the smart contract methods
is that right
yeah yeah that's that's correct and I
guess one other thing to mention oh yeah
that was a pretty good overview so you
sir you know you have your Zrii your
front-end layer that's pretty standard
and this is sort of also somehow hooked
up you know probably using one of these
wallets to sort of sign and send
transactions into the etherium Network
and there's a one of the common solidity
patterns is this concept of events so
event firing you know one of the things
that's still a little bit difficult is
sort of you know historical state
introspection of smart contracts so you
can't you need some layer there that's
sort of listening to aetherium and when
these events are logged they typically
need to be stored somewhere else
you kind of have the cycle of you know
firing of it like you know sign a
message saying you want to do something
the smart contracts gonna run then it
will fire an event and you have some
sort of service that's probably
listening and it might take that event
and pop it into something more queryable
than aetherium so you probably have some
sort of some of the states gonna be
copied
to your back-end into something that's
more queryable you know like post grass
or something like that so you know the
UI can get some of these updates
a little quicker than trying to figure
them out directly from the node itself
god yeah yeah that's a that's a key
point you know that we can use some of
these events and state changes and you
know maybe index them over in a more
queryable database in terms of going
into the details of smart contact itself
you mentioned solidity is the language
used today most commonly let's dive into
what smart contracts are and like maybe
pick up a couple examples from real
world you know what what is the kind of
business logic that goes into smart
contracts I've also heard a lot of
people saying that smart contracts could
also be legal contracts so I want to get
into the details of you know different
types of smart contracts that exist
today how real they are sure yeah so
smart contracts they're as you mentioned
most commonly written in solidity and
you know they're really at the end of
the day they're kind of just code that's
a you know stored in the blockchain that
anyone can interact with you know this
is a an interesting paradigm that we
didn't really have before I can't really
go inspect all the code that's you know
in executable form that's on your
private server so this is a pretty
interesting new paradigm and the way
they're being used since you can sort of
you know code arbitrary things into your
smart contract there's a lot of emphasis
on sort of standards around you know
just what's the goal of this smart
contract and I think that's one of the
things that the etherium community
community has been really good at is you
know having there's you know public
discussion for various smart contract
standards so for example many people are
probably familiar with you know what
happened in 2017 there's this like
insane ico boom
people just raising absurd sons sums of
money superfast on the internet and you
know part of that was sort of possible
because of this really good ability to
sort of standardize and come to
agreement around what sort of API or
smart contract would have so in
aetherium they have these you know ERC
these like the sort of github issues for
discussing and coming to conclusions
around what kind of features you need in
a smart contract and so one of the most
popular ones or more famous ones is a
ERC 20 so this is sort of the simple
token smart contract and this is what
allowed all these different tokens to
like be generated and then also sort of
interact with each other so that's
probably one of the most used smart
contracts that's out there another more
recent one that's been pretty
interesting is the ERC 7:21 so ERC 20 i
was not as a fungible token meaning just
meaning there that leo one token is the
same as any other token so if you have a
balance of one token it's gonna be the
same like my balance of one token is the
same as your balance of one token
whereas ERC 7:21 is a non fungible token
and basically this just means that you
know as far as the data structure is
concerned the token is the same and so
you might think of something like a
house deed where you know my house deed
has the similar data structure to your
house deed however if your house deed
says that you own the house by the water
and mine says you know I own the house
by the freeway those house needs are not
and it's sort of exchangeable they're
not one for one and so there's now a lot
of interesting work you know as you can
imagine there's the non fungible token
standard is really interesting even free
no like something you mentioned as far
as like a legal contract or like you
know house deed might be is it kind of a
legal instrument so uh yeah there's a
lot of work and kind of research into
that space so yeah you mentioned
something like ER c is the adhesion
request for comments and that's hot
that's how a lot of the community
gets around the you know the consensus
building on what the standards for
different types of tokens would be so er
C 20 you mentioned earlier for you know
this move the most standardized across
which a lot of ice use have raised
tokens and then more recently the 721
right there's also a IPS which are more
like the improvement proposals and I
guess they are more they have a larger
scope for the protocol or the helium you
know improvements that are going on when
coming back to the ERC 20 yeah so yeah
the EIP is you know more like protocol
level changes if there's maybe I wanted
to propose a solution for you know a
superior solution for ordering
transactions or you know something kind
of on the low level you know a lot of
the you know scaling is a very big topic
in aetherium right now you know how are
we gonna achieve high throughput you
know what are we gonna do with all this
data the blockchain is growing sort of
exponentially so like you know how are
we gonna shard the data like what is
this gonna look like you know
proof-of-work is a pretty simple
consensus mechanism stake has a lot more
two components to it so those kind of
protocol discussions happen in the e IPS
and then the ERC is more sort of
application layer like if we want to
write code that's you know interoperable
you know sort of at the EVM layer
whereas the EIP is sort of protocol
layer that's great to differentiate
thanks a lot and on the ERC side you
mentioned GRC 20 as a standard open for
you know for which people are you know
defining the application tokens or even
the I cos can we get into a little bit
of a detail on say an example of what er
C 20 actually defines and you know maybe
even picking up on an example token that
exists sure so there are your kind of
tons and tons of different er C 20
tokens you know representing all sorts
of various things yeah and make it kind
of it totally ranges so they could
people can just one of the interesting
things here is you know you can just
issue or your own and sort of say
and you're kind of whatever you want but
some one of the more interesting ones
are you know people are experimenting
with using these tokens to sort of you
know pay for distributed storage or you
know specific types of processing so
there's a project called golem you know
not the Lord of the Rings but um so the
golem token the idea there is that you
know you could sort of turn on your
computer and let other people perform
computation tasks that you might not
want to perform directly in the EVM so I
think golems starting with sort of video
rendering like animated video rendering
I think this is like pretty you know I'm
not an expert in this but it's seen what
they discusses it's very computationally
intensive and it'd be pretty interesting
if you could sort of submit a job to the
network people who were there offering
their services would then render the
video for you and send it back and you
might pay them in gold and tokens so
this is a new example of an existing ERC
20 token I think they're not in
production but they do have a number of
sort of like beta tools out there that
you can use and so kind of participate
in this network
Kocher it's a pretty good example of how
these tokens are being used
you mentioned distributed storage you
mentioned you know calling for you know
the more computing aspect of it and when
I see that I also try and compare that
to how how we use computing today like
we have a whole commoditized cloud out
there and you can use it for genetic
computing you know defining applications
running them scaling them and it's
amazing how that is now done more
decentralized with protocols like column
yeah absolutely I mean you know there in
it I think it's interesting just you
know like you mentioned there are sort
of some of these tools out there they're
you know useful and they work very well
today but uh kind of like the
decentralized permissionless aspects
they're pretty interesting in the
employee providing
different solutions right so so let's
get into the details of how to even
write a smart contract and you know I
think we discussed a couple languages
that we use the most famous ones of them
is solidity so what is this language
like sure you know it definitely has
definitely has its quirks but um you
know it's it's kind of similar to you
know maybe go in JavaScript maybe like a
little bit mixed together so it's sort
of an object-oriented software
architecture you can inherit from other
smart contracts you can have a smart
contract that's you know interacting
with a separate one you can sort of
spawn you know generate you kind of have
like this sort of factory architecture
you might have a smart contract that
makes new smart contracts but in general
anyone familiar with object-oriented
programming is probably not going to
have too much difficulty picking up
solidity and in in general like what are
the basic constructs that one would
start with if if doing like the 101 of
solidity sure so you know this sort of
the hello world of a solidity contract
would be the simple storage contract so
you know one of the simplest things you
can do is update state so you know maybe
you're just storing a number in the
blockchain and then you want to go query
that number later so this is kind of the
the classic hello world for aetherium is
getting simple storage up and running
and yeah you know if you were looking to
get started I'd say the you know the
solidity Doc's are an okay place to it's
kind of poke around there's a couple
different sort of like standards bodies
out there working on sort of like
audited you know community vetted smart
contracts so if people want to look up
the Zeppelin smart contracts those are
pretty good to get start with they come
with a number of things so you could you
know create your own token you know do a
couple of these were like boilerplate
set up features if you just wanted to
get something going kinda like playing
around it'd be a good place to start
that's yeah
so that's that's about solidity as is a
smart contract development language are
there are some examples that one would
start with if if new to solidity and
look at some of the more complex type of
smart contracts in you know more more
specifically compared to a real-world
logic of you know why would someone do a
smart contract say for payments or you
know for how we say removing the
middleman in certain transactions sure
yeah I mean you know some of the sort of
classic ones are like you know smart
contracts are really good as registries
you know if you wanted to sort of you
know written and we talked about like an
identity a little bit but you can
register various addresses that
represent certain things
another classic one is sort of the
escrow smart contract you know if I
wanted to write a web app that sort of
escrow dollars I don't really know
exactly how I'd go about it I might
investigate who knows like stripe or
something like that but it's sort of
trivial in solidity which is pretty
interesting so you know I'd probably
talk around with the check out the
escrow smart contract another pretty
interesting one is investments we're
playing around the multi-sig smart
contracts an interesting one and you can
combine the two sort of have a multi-sig
escrow smart contract some of those are
probably good places to get started and
kind of understandings for what you can
do with the solidity language gotcha
that's a pretty good example so if you
know how we can begin with like looking
at some real world smart contracts and
I'll definitely put some links out there
in the show notes just so that audience
can also look at some of the basic smart
contracts so John now that we've covered
solidity and you know different types of
you know smart contracts and also the
fact that there are token standards what
what is the in energist like what is the
etherium application for for someone new
that is coming into the ecosystem sure
so at the end of the day like gaps you
know they're not totally different than
you know we mentioned they're not
totally different than sort of existing
app architecture but the interesting
piece is that you can
answer this permission list restless
layer that you can really have before
you know so if you you know we're
building sort of a Craigslist app you
know distributed Craigslist and you
wanted to have proof that somebody was
actually interested in buying your couch
and they weren't just gonna flake on you
the next day you might have and the
ability for you know somebody the escrow
funds sort of just built straight into
the app and this is kind of amazing and
that you just need you know a few lines
of solidity and the ability for somebody
this sort of you know sign and transfer
funds you know bills straight into the
app you know a lot of the UI the UI
developments probably is pretty much the
sort of the same as anybody's used to
the difference there is you just now
have you know a part of your apps API is
going to be sort of interacting with
this library called web three it's
probably the most it's like the main way
that people sort of sign messages it's a
JavaScript based tool so it's you know a
lot of these apps are browser-based but
it sort of allows people to do this
message signing in the browser and then
kind of you know pull the wait and see
you know when their messages have been
submitted so as far as that level goes
that's kind of just that's pretty
standard and sort of the interesting
part the next part of the architecture
that you know is blockchain specific
would be sort of you know waiting to see
if your message is going to be accepted
by the network so this is sort of an
interesting interesting problem that you
don't typically have to deal with with
when building applications usually
you're you know you're not waiting for
your database to tell you that you know
something's happened you know things are
happening nearly instantaneously and
that's not quite the keys the case with
sort of existing blockchain
architectures so once message is
assigned you do need some sort of
service layers that are giving your app
feedback as to like has the message you
know the transaction been proud
did it get rejected for some reason then
you have to kind of deal with that
probably not only in your back end but
also in sarira at the application layer
of the DAP so I think in some part you
also dived into the the ui/ux approaches
for creating an Akita map and you
mentioned that there are certain
principles in UX that might not be you
know as similar to a traditional web app
where you've got access to some really
fast event databases and event streams
which it helium you know probably is not
going to give you an an instant you know
query result any particular you know
development or testing approaches that
you have found useful for you know
developing gaps as it the main sort of
you know the main gap test solution or
like one of the more common ones is your
truffle is quite common so you're just
you're just writing lots of you know
JavaScript tests that sort of mock out
interaction with the with the DAP itself
and you'll actually so you know the sort
of a common pattern there is like okay
have a you know written up reasonably
sized solidity smart contract you can
imagine you want to be pretty sure it's
gonna do what you think it's gonna do
especially if your contracts you know
escrowing funds or anything like that
and say you know you'll write out a
comprehensive test suite and then you'll
have you know this setup where you'll
kind of deploy a new smart contract
maybe seed it with some data and then
start you know just going through unit
tests for you know yet I guess you know
tests and integration tests for what
users could possibly be doing with the
smart contract and making sure you get
the expected behavior right yeah
in terms of testing though so you
mentioned earlier that people use local
blockchain for just quick development
and and are trading on you know
debugging they're the smart contracts
yeah and then there's also this concept
of a test net and we go into the like a
life cycle itself of a DAP project like
how does one get it you know these
different stages of getting to the
that gotcha shirt so um yeah so I guess
the you know the place you start is sort
of getting a node up and running locally
and these will have you know there's a
couple different ones out there they're
gonna have superfast block confirmation
times and the reason you can set this is
you're the only node in the network so
you can you know agree with yourself
that the transactions are valid pretty
quickly so you'll have this set up and
you'll be kind of configured to like
deploy against this network and run some
tests so this would be hat you know
while you're sort of in development
adding new features you know you can go
ahead and write a test you know TDD is
still probably the most standard way
smart contract developments done it's a
write a test you know it can fail
implement the feature in your smart
contract you know get it to pass and
kind of iteratively
iteratively go through this till your
smart contracts kind of doing what you
needed to be doing and then the next
step would be deploying to one of the
other sort of testing one of the other
test test networks that simulate what
the live Nets like there's a couple of
them you know rinkeby is a quite popular
test net Rob standard test net and so
then after you you know they're done
testing against your local node you
might also deploy to that environment
run your test there once things look
like they're passing you're then gonna
go ahead and deploy to the main net and
sort of the interesting thing here is
you would probably then not run your you
know your production smart contractor
you know you're probably not going to
run your test framework against it so
you might deploy to the maintenance run
some tests the interesting thing though
here to note is that you'll be sort of
paying per test as we discussed earlier
you know you have to pay per
computations so if you have a very large
comprehensive test suite it's going to
be quite expensive to test it on the
maintenance
gotcha that'sthat's very interesting as
a as a problem in itself that you know
every time you do a transaction be it
you know testing or a real life you know
production transaction on the main that
you you'd probably pay a gas in terms of
the local node are there some tools that
help you set up a local node without
connecting to each idiom
yeah sure so yeah there's a whole bunch
of different you know tools out there
you can I believe there's one called the
JavaScript one it's called ganash kind
of goes with that a smart contract tool
truffle there's a tool strata that's
pretty easy to get up and running
locally you can just install some docker
containers and you know sort of start it
early building your smart contracts
there's another sort of hosted solution
called in fira that will you know let
you test things i think both asher and
amazon also offer sort of blockchain
nodes that are pretty easy to spin up
and start going and i think they have
you know you can run sort of test
environments or if you want to run like
a live net environment you can also run
that god yeah
and then when you are actually moving
code from local to test net is there a
set up that is explicitly required to
get your application some funds to to
run on the test net yep there definitely
are so there's a number of different i
guess is this concept of a faucet so you
know on the test nets you know your
local node might have just a totally
open faucet you might have when you you
know sort of turn the blockchain on
there's this idea of the Genesis block
and so you can kind of configure some of
the properties of your blockchain in
then in that file and so for testing you
might have this faucet that you know
when the blockchain turns on there's one
account with an enormous amount of ether
can kind of use that to run all your
tests then on the you know some of those
more public test Nets like rinkeby or
robson they kind of they have publicly
available faucets that you can sort of
send the you know ask
small amounts either to gonna run your
tests and stuff like that
Roger and looking at the smart contracts
that you know we discussed in the the
development tooling that exists let's
just come back to the the main that it
sells like how how many of these smart
contracts that we have seen in the
ecosystem over the past couple years
have actually made it to the main that
and then within those that have been
there on the live net what have become
of off more like that the usage of those
smart contracts and try to get to a
point where we have seen a lot of smart
contracts in in development but how many
of them have actually gotten to the
production grade yeah so I'd say more of
them have not quite made it to the live
net than have but there's a you know
there's quite a few that are out there
in the wild a shameless plug here but
you know the product I work on is a
blockchain based art collecting platform
called super air so you know there's you
know which incorporates kind of like a
marketplace and there's you know a
number of these kind of you know the
gaming ones are also pretty popular and
you know crypto kitties they kind of
pioneered the ERC 7:21 smart contract
architecture so there's a bunch of these
sort of non fungible token applications
that are being put out and being used in
production as I mentioned that you port
identity solutions now in the
maintenance there's a project called
meta X that runs a sort of online
advertising registry and I think after
about a year of sort of like
architecting and testing they're now in
production on the live net so that's
pretty exciting and that's a they're
using an architecture that I think we
haven't talked about yet called a token
curated registry
anybody who's interested in smart
contract architecture probably be
interested in reading and reading up on
TC RS as they're called so yeah I'd say
probably the most common things that are
sort of in production on the on the live
net are sort of token smart contracts
there's a number of various exchanges
for these tokens token curated
registries are also quite popular
and then sort of identity solutions B I
guess the three sort of types of kind of
common smart contracts that are out
there that's great and thanks for
mentioning TC arts you know I definitely
include that in the notes so so now that
these exist in in the wild and people
are using them what have you seen of the
service providers coming into this space
to help you know develop test and maybe
even you know operationalize some of the
production ready applications into the
theater ecosystem sure you know I think
as we mentioned both Azure and amazon
offer kind of boilerplate templates to
get you know get nodes up and running
pretty quickly as far as like tooling
and stuff you know truffle is quite
popular you know there's some sort of
comprehensive test that you know so like
depending on how you know into the
nitty-gritty you want to get if you just
want something you know off-the-shelf
that you can kind of turn on there's you
know as your offer is some pretty good
tooling around that you know I mentioned
Strato and some of these other sort of
block chains that you can do and just
like turn on instantly and then have you
know your setup kind of ready to go with
you know some of the key management and
things like that and fear is also you
know a really popular one you know it's
quite heavily used they also support
life via IP FS which is interesting if
you want to kind of play around with
some of the distributed file storage
properties gotcha and in terms of the
you know the smart contract testing
itself is there you know is there a way
to reduce the risk of these security
bugs that we have seen over the last
couple years because we play with funds
and there's a bunch of you know things
that are always dealing with you know
live either on the main net how would
one as a smart contract developer go
about securing or maybe even been
testing some of that yeah sure so I mean
you know one of the more common ways is
you know a lot of this development is
happening on github so there's sort of
an auditing period people also pretty
common practice to put up bug bounties
for new smart contracts especially if
they're you know doing something
slightly less standard than
use some of the other things that are
already out there this is one of the
more common ways to kind of incentivize
people to help test your your code but I
think it's one of the interesting
challenges you know if it's uh if you're
doing something new and you know you
haven't written a test case for
something that's not really there's not
a whole lot of automated solutions I
think there are you know people are
working on you know more formal
verification and smart contract
frameworks and there's some interesting
auditing tools out there I think one's
called quant stamp that does some sort
of automated sort of solidity auditing
but it's still I think that area is
still something that um is you know in
active development gotcha
and between like the open source and
more off the shelf you know services
that you mentioned earlier that are
available on you know major cloud
providers you're saying that a lot of a
lot of the ecosystem still thrives on
open source yeah it's it's a pretty it's
definitely very open source driven kind
of in the ethos of the ecosystems gotcha
yeah that was also one of the most
beautiful aspect of etherium in general
itself that you know if you look at the
ecosystem that has evolved so far you
know everything including development
governance you know the protocol
proposals are all happening in the open
source and that's you know that's what I
think is also driving this community
together in some sense there's you know
there's nothing hidden when it comes to
you know the changes that are coming
live on on the minute and how much time
it has taken to actually vet those
changes you're just picking on that
adoption curve though there's there's
definitely a lot of speculation around
where you know the p2p aspect of this is
coming at the peer to peer removing the
intermediary getting things
decentralized but there's also obviously
a net new you know wave of applications
that are coming up like replica tees for
example right going back to your
experience as as a founder like as a
developer on aetherium you know and as a
product manager earlier on what have you
seen as maybe some of the learnings
in an architectural patterns that have
evolved and then I wanted to like do a
deep dive on you know just the way you
know pick Syrah and super rare came
about yeah I'd say you know one of the
bigger learnings that you sort of
everybody is experienced in the space is
that um you want to leverage what block
chains are good at when they're good at
what you're doing and if it's not ideal
for what you're trying to do then that's
a pretty clear sign you probably do not
want to be you know putting that part of
your application into the block chain
you know as we discussed you know
solidity is an evolving language it's
being used in production but you know
it's still early days with a lot of
these projects and you know I'd say the
the best smart contracts are you know
small and you know easily easy to read
audited you don't want to be you know
especially when you are dealing with
funds you know you don't want a huge
complicated smart contract that's a you
know gonna have some critical you know
flaws in it so sort of just as little as
you can write into the smart contract is
a good place to be
so just to be mindful of that when you
are developing let's say that's one of
the biggest lessons that you know that
I've learned that you and in in all the
architectures that we're seeing evolving
right now in the decentralized space can
you cover some of the most important
ones that you have been you know maybe
looking at involve being or even the
ones that interest you the most across
different domains you know one thing
that's come up a lot in this
conversation in just in general as the
space is the yes or the different
architectures around identity I think
there's a few you know identity is at
least in aetherium you know it's in sort
of the smart contract layer so there's a
number of ERC proposals out there for
different identity solutions and so yeah
there's still a lot of conversation
happening if anybody's interested you
know you can go
so check them out on github which is
pretty interesting but um yeah I think
identity is one of the interesting ones
just cuz the sort of like key recovery
you know what happens if your keys get
stolen there's a lot of things to think
about so that's probably one of the more
complicated architectural patterns out
there you know in finance you know
there's a ton of work people are talking
a lot about security tokens and you know
what does this mean there's an
interesting project called Pangea that's
you know sort of tokenizing shares of
real estate so if you wanted to add some
liquidity to the value in your house you
could tokenize and let investors or
trade it in the free market so I think
this is an interesting pattern and sort
of taking existing illegal securities
and then moving part of them onto the
blockchain so I think we'll see a lot
more of that mmm it's kind of an
interesting space to watch you know
there's a lot of work happening in the
healthcare space I think some of them
are you know the majority of what I'm
saying is sort of around access to data
so data ownership so it's pretty closely
related to you know the work that's
being done with identity some of the
differences here being you know like
there might be certain cases where you
wanted a doctor to have access to data
and maybe you know a patient might not
be conscious to like grant the access so
you know there's some interesting use
cases there and things to be sorted out
so there's a pretty active development
that in that space is a number of
different healthcare projects and yeah
you know as I mentioned one of the one
ones it's close to my heart is sort of
you know in the art space it's you know
it's pretty interesting to think about
you know art on the internet you know
how does this work but you know a lot of
what we've been doing with super rare
and Pixar is sort of digging into the
you know none fungible token use case
and seeing how we can apply it to you
know the creation of art in an online
manner so the collection of art online
you know experimenting with sort of what
does this look like in the and that's
pretty interesting space because it is
digital native you mentioned its
creation of art itself in an online
manner you dig a little bit deeper into
how like what is super rare and like
what is the you know
the value prop what are you guys trying
to like solve sure you know in a
nutshell super air is a place for you
know artists and creators who are you
know whose work is digitally native to
sort of you know register their work
online and then also you have a way for
sort of collectors to interact with it
it's interesting to think about so you
know now we have you know we have a lot
of these decentralized tools you know
they're you know they also have tools
for like value transfers so basically
we're letting artists create their own
tokens that represent specific pieces of
work and then they cannot you know they
can sort of just have these you know
these are new tokens that start to sit
in your wallet and the artist can you
know they could just upload them if they
want to just have their work sitting
there or they can offer it up for sale
and you know one of the fun things we've
been playing around with super air is
like thinking about like okay so you
have you know and in art there's this
concept at the primary market and then
secondary markets and so we spend a lot
of time thinking about that and we're
like okay be pretty it'd be really
interesting if for secondary market
trades you could pay royalties to the
original creator of the work you know
sort of is like you know a thank you
especially if you know you bought
something when an artist was you know
not very well known and then later on if
the works appreciated quite a lot in
value I'd be pretty cool to you know
sort of pay tribute or pay royalties to
the original creator so currently on
super air the artists get you know the
full portion of the sale on the primary
market and then in secondary markets
they also get a royalty cut of the
exchange fee I think that's pretty
interesting
on how you deal with both the primary
and the secondary market aspect of this
in once the original art has been sold
you're saying that a new transaction
beyond that point would still have
royalties to the the main artist right
that's correct so in the just in the
smart contract when you calls are like
if you know someone's
the works of for sale and you're
interacting with a smart contract saying
you want to buy it if it's you know
after the first time the works sold the
smart contract will do a little bit of
math and kind of pay the appropriate
parties their share so you know it's you
know it's a simple you know feature in
the smart contract but it's a pretty
interesting use case in my mind you know
it sort of opens up you know a whole new
way to interact with the work and you
think about like you know paying
attribution to the creators and things
like that great so so what's your go-to
reference for all things that helium and
like more generally in the blockchain
space when you get most of your iam
reading references strong for aetherium
specific things I'd say my go-to
references are probably the etherium
subreddit and then also the etherium dev
subreddit those are you know to my
favorites and you know the etherium
subreddits you know sort of just general
state of affairs and the devlins pretty
good for you know just looking at new
tools or experimental projects that have
come out we're sort of just like
blockchain ecosystem things in general
I'd say Laura shins Unchained podcast is
one of my go-to that's a really good one
I definitely recommend everybody check
that out and then for a pretty good
overview newsletter there's a newsletter
called token economy that's one of my
favorites so I'd say if you're paying
attention to those three you're probably
you know reasonably up-to-date and and
by yourself do you do you blog or you
know write something on medium or do you
have any favorite links that you'd like
to add onto the notes sure so yeah you
can find that you know I probably write
the most under super rare on medium so
sure go ahead and just follow super err
on Twitter and follow us on medium you
know we try to write you know maybe once
a week or so about just you know what
we're doing you know it's a mix of sort
of the business side of things or also
just
the architecture technical side of
things great and how do people reach out
to you you need twitter handy sure yep
so you can go ahead and reach out to me
on Twitter at NARS Li that's a G n AR z
ly cool I'll include that in the notes
John so so great to have you here on the
on the show thanks a lot for spending
some time you know doing a general
overview of the ecosystem and deep dives
on smart contracts and in you know
generally these examples that you
presented on what kind of smartphone
tracks have come about in the in the
main net so far again thanks a lot for
you know skills for sharing this sure
thing
you know thanks so much for having week
sure really appreciate it thanks this
was Kishore Bhatia for software
engineering video thanks digitalocean is
the easiest cloud platform to deploy
manage and scale applications of any
size we're moving infrastructure
friction and providing predictability so
developers and their teams can deploy
faster and focus on building software
that customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/ SC radio thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by Archer police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website @ SC -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se Radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening
you